A Guide to the Angelica Schuyler Church Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Papers
  - Philip John Schuyler, Albany, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1790 October 20; ALS, 2 p.
    Received word that the Churches were in France for "the 14th of July bash" [Bastille Day]; news of the family.
  - Philip John Schuyler, New York, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1793 February 6; ALS, 3 p.
    Support of her philantrophy. He states that he will carry into effect her wishes in favor of Lafayette and also that he wishes that he could say that he "shall be immediately released, and cherished by America..." but "prudential reasons added to political ones will prevent an immediate application thru the channel you support..." He indicates that it would be more appropriate for the central government to have passed an act "conferring a handsome annuity on the M. De Lafayette and his lady, together with a grant of an extensive tract of land---" #11245-a
  - Philip John Schuyler, "Shelmahr," to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1793 May 25; ALS, 3 p.
    Mentions that he has pointed out a purchase to Mr. [John Barker] Church which appears that it will prove to be productive; discusses the area around the Mohawk River in New York, including the growth of the area; mentions son Philip Schuyler.
  - Philip John Schuyler, New York, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1794 May 12; ALS, 2 p.
    Refers to Mr. [John] Jay and Col. [John] Trumbulll, advocates of [John Barker] Church; mentions Margaret Schuyler van Rensselaer.
  - Philip John Schuyler, New York, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1795 April 17; ALS, 3 p.
    Mentions the arrival of her ship at Rhode Island, concern over the serious conditions present in England and in Europe, v and Monsieur and Madam Grovernel. He comments on a book containing the drawing of the telegraph first seen in America. He discusses the Duke de Liancourt [Liancoeur?]. Writes that he has attended his duty in the Senate from the beginning of January to early April, and comments on his political opponents. Mentions Cornelia [Schuyler], Alexander and Elizabeth (Schuyler) Hamilton; Margaret [Schuyler van Rensselaer], and Catharine [Church Cruger]. Concern for Marquis de Lafayette and his suffering.
  - Philip John Schuyler, Albany, New York, to John Barker Church., 1796 June 13; ALS, 2 p.
    Introduces Rufus King (1755-1827), ambassador to Great Britain in London from the United States, and comments on his virtues. Discusses land mortgaged in the county of Ontario and debt due by John Barker Church.
  - Philip John Schuyler to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1797 December 7; ALS, 3 p.
    Affectionate and loving letter from a father to his daughter. Mentions Cornelia [Schuyler] and their reconciliation, [Stephen] van Rensselaer and his being capable of reform and of a return to virtue, and Philip [Schuyler] and his studies.
  - Philip John Schuyler, Albany, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church, New York, New York., 1804 August 4; LS, 2 p.
    Grief and sorrow over the death of Alexander Hamilton, and sympathy for his wife, Elizabeth Schuyler Hamilton, and their children.
  - Winfield Scott, West Point, New York, to J. C. Cruger., 1865 June 21; ALS, 4 p.
    Writes his pleasure following a visit by J. C. and Catharine Church Cruger and their daughters; complimented by a request for a "memento of the oldest soldier of the age--I mean the oldest in commission."
  - Winfield Scott to Cornelia Cruger, with ANS to "Kitty" Cruger., 1865; LS, 2 p.
    Two autographs to the daughters of J. C. and Catharine Church Cruger.
  - M. De Nilavy, Olmutz, Austria, to [Angelica Schuyler Church]., n.d.[ca. 1795]; ALS, 3 p.
    Probably an attempt to effect the escape of Monsieur de Lafayette from the Austrian prison at Olmutz through the offices of American diplomats [Thomas] Pinckney and [John] Jay.
  - Elinor M. Squier to Peter [ ]., n.y. Christmas; ALS, 1 p.
    [1789] November 7 ALS, 4 p. Friedrich Wilhelm Ludolf Augustin, Baron von Steuben, New York, New York, to Angelica Schuyler Church. [In French. An affectionate letter written on her departure. Mentions [Alexander and Elizabeth Schuyler] Hamilton, "Peggy" [Margaret Schuyler van Rensselaer.
  - Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Perigord, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1794 May 11; ALS, 4 p.
    In French. Sends news of her father. Mentions Philadelphia, praises [Alexander] Hamilton, mentions the Marquis de Lafayette, and hopes John Jay will restore harmony between the United States and England, conveys travel plans and news of Louis-Marie Noailles who is settling down as an American.
  - Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Perigord, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1794 June 10; ALS, 2 p.
    In French. Mentions the kindness shown [Alexander] Hamilton, and General [Philip John] Schuyler. A friend of Lafayette's will deliver the letter. Mentions [John Barker] Church, and others.
  - Stephen van Rensselaer, Oswegatchie and Ogdensburg, New York, to Rensselaer Westerlo (1776-1851), Albany, New York., 1812 July 25; LS, 2 p.
    Describes the atmosphere in Oswegatchie while a British Sloop of War was anchored offshore; mentions Sackets Harbor, Oswego, the Turnpike, and Geneva, New York.
  - Stephen van Rensselaer, Lewiston, New York, to Rensselaer Westerlo, Albany, New York., 1812 September 1; LS, 2 p.
    News of Queenstown [sic], Ontario, Canada; mentions General [Isaac] Brock (1769-1812), Major [ ] Evan, and General Sheaffe; refers to confirmation of armistice.
  - Stephen van Rensselaer, Lewiston, New York, to Rensselaer Westerlo, Albany, New York., 1812 September 17; ALS, 1 p.
    Gives instructions for Cornelia [Paterson van Rensselaer] to order cloth from the Shakers; relates briefly the condition of life for the men in their tents.
  - Stephen van Rensselaer, Lewiston, New York, to Rensselaer Westerlo, Albany, New York., 1812 October 8; LS, 1 p.
    Mentions the illness of the Colonel, [Abraham] Van Vechten (1762-1837), and Peter [Buell] Porter (1773-1844). Relates uncomfortable condition of life for the men in their tents.
  - Stephen van Rensselaer, Lewiston, New York, to Rensselaer Westerlo, Albany, New York., 1812 October 15; ALS, 2 p.
    Details the attack, and the ensuing battle, on the British at Queenstown [sic], Ontario, Canada; mentions the fates of several soldiers, including General [Isaac] Brock who was fatally wounded, General Wadsworth, and the Colonel.
  - E[lizabeth] W. van Rensselaer, Edinburgh, England, to Nicholas Low, London, England., 1840 August 10; ALS, 3 p.
    Relates the sightseeing adventures of herself and Cornelia [van Rensselaer] and their mother [Cornelia Paterson van Rensselaer]; mentions travelling to the cathedrals, castles, abbeys, and palaces throughout England; visits to Abbotsford, residence of Sir Walter Scott (1771-1832), and Newstead Abbey, ancestral mansion of George Gordon Byron, Lord Byron (1788-1824); and, plans to visit Paris, France.
  - George Washington, Philadelphia, Pennsylavania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1798 December 4; LS, 1 p.
    Expresses gratitude for her "very obliging and flattering sentiments"; assures her of her son's "future usefulness & consequence," mentions General [Alexander] Hamilton's "favorable report of his merits," and offers any assistance.
  - George Washington, Mount Vernon, Virginia, to The Cashier of the Office of Discount & Deposit--Baltimore., 1799 April 28; ANS Robert Spring forgery,
    Order to pay Richard Caton from his account.
  - [ ], Paris, France, to Angelica Schuyler Church, London, England., 1784 June 30; ALS, 3 p.
    In French. Invitation to the family farm near Paris. Mentions "Peggy" [Margaret Schuyler van Rensselaer], [John Barker] Church, and others.
  - [ ], Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Angelica Schuyler Church., 1794 March 6; ALS, 8 p.
    In French. Comments on the behavior and appearance of the American people. Mentions [Alexander] Hamilton, General [Philip John] Schuyler, Philadelphia, Talleyrand [Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Perigord], [John] Trumbull, [John] Jay, [ ] Talon, Monsieur de Noailles, Marquis and Madam de Lafayette, and [John Barker] Church. Also, probably an attempt to effect the escape of Monsieur de Lafayette from the Austrian prison Olmutz. Mentions the refugee colony at Azilum [Asylum], Pa.
  - [ ] to John Church., n.d.; ALS (incomplete), 4 p.
    Life and career experiences of this American merchant who was apparently compelled to leave his home country for India for his own safety; comments on the relationship of the American merchants and the notorious rogues in the Bengal Trade; relates that he employs his time and capital in the interior trade and in the manufacturing of sugar and indigo; refers to the affection and support of Mrs. "B."
  - Order of Exercises..., 1864 July 4; AMs, 2 p.
    Independence Day exercises in Red Hook, New York.
- Oversize Tray 58
  - Indenture between George Remsen, Daniel Ludlow, and Rem P. Remsen for the sale of the real estate of David Provost, for land in New York, 1786 July 29; Ds